- Hey folks and welcome
to the Learn UI design lesson on spacing.
Spacing is one of the most
fundamental and important skills
that you, as the designer can
work on and get better at.
It's something that
you're going to be using
in basically every design
project you ever do.
Doesn't matter whether it's a web app
or a mobile app or
something else entirely,
it doesn't matter whether you're trying
to have just like a very
clean and simple brand
or a friendly brand or
any other type of brand,
any platform, you're going
to be using white space,
and you're going to be thinking
about the lessons from this video.
So we're gonna look at a
couple of examples today.
We're just going to talk
about how spacing applies
in a wide variety of applications.
And we're going to talk
about in particular four
rules, laws, heuristics
to remember when you're
applying white space
to your own designs, but the
overarching theme if anything,
that I'd like you to walk
away with is the sense
that white space is a
really special element,
If you can call it an element.
Because it's the only thing
that you will ever add
to your design, that doesn't
clutter it in some way.
And by clutter, I mean just
add some visual distractingness
to the design, right?
Even the smallest lightest
little one pixel divider line
is going to add something
to the screen that kind of,
you know, adds clutter,
white space does not.
And yet you can communicate
with white space,
you can use white space to
say what things are related.
You can use white space to
say what things are important.
So remember that,
it's the only thing that can
communicate without cluttering.
Alright, would that being
said, let's get started.
I'm going to begin just
by telling you these four laws of spacing.
And I don't necessarily expect
that you're going to understand all
of these perfectly right now.
That's why we have a whole
bunch of examples coming up
but I just want to kind
of get these primed
in your mind so that as you
see them in the examples,
you understand what I'm
referencing back to.
Four of the most important
things you can remember
with regards to spacing.
Number one, you can use white space
to separate without cluttering.
I'm going to be showing you some examples
that kind of illustrate
how to some degree,
separator lines, background color changes
even cards or shadows
are all kind of instances
of elements that are
supposed to divide one area
of the screen from another area
and how white space
also does the same thing
but it does it without cluttering.
That's probably the most important lesson.
Number two, we're gonna be
talking about how white space
can be used to highlight
focal points in your design.
If you have an important
element, there's a whole bunch
of things you can do to attract attention.
Like you could make it really, really big
or really, really colorful,
but a slightly more
subtle option is to give it
a lot of spacing around it.
And especially if you're
trying to have a clean,
simple and uncluttered
design, that's going to be one
of the go-to ways to draw
attention to certain focal points.
The third law is that external spacing
should always be greater
than internal spacing.
And I'll explain what I mean by this
but it basically means
whenever you have some sort
of group of elements that kind
of logically fit together,
the spacing around that
group should be greater
than the spacing in between
the elements of that group.
And I mean that in a very broad way, again
we're going to be talking
about it, but I just
want to introduce the idea now.
And the fourth law,
I promise you, I only
mean this figuratively,
but double your white space.
White space is one of
the things that at least
for me and for many
other beginning designers
you need to use more
of it than you suspect.
Does this mean you should
actually take your first guess
and literally double it?
No, it doesn't, but it does mean
that many great designs
use more white space
that if you were to go and measure it,
which I encourage you
to, through copy work,
or just on the fly, you would find
that they're using quite a bit of spacing
and we want to do the exact same thing.
The first example we're
going to be looking at today
is Craigslist and
Craigslist gets a little bit
of a bad rap among visual designers,
just because it's so garishly simplistic
and unstyled that it just, it
doesn't really feel designed.
It's certainly anything but pretty.
So we're going to be doing a
little bit of visual touch up
on the interface, and
we're primarily going
to be using the principles
of white space to do it.
I will also be honest.
We're going to be using
plenty of alignment.
So if you haven't watched that lesson,
it's a useful thing that we're
going to reference a bunch,
and a few other ideas from
the fundamentals in this unit.
Now I just want to be clear,
this is very much a demo.
Craigslist has made the design choices
that it has for very specific reasons.
Like for instance,
I know they want to load
their page very, very quickly.
There are basically no
images on this page.
Even their logo is the letters
C and L in plain Arial.
But since we're doing a visual touch-up
for an educational exercise, we can throw
that out the window
and decide for instance
to use some custom fonts
or include other icons
or whatever we want to.
So just bear in mind
that we may be doing things
that are not necessarily part
of Craigslists business goals.
All right, so let's take it from the top.
I mean, literally at the top
we've got this header
element 44 pixels tall.
It goes the full width of the screen.
Now, one thing that's interesting
about this header element is it's gray
and basically the entire rest
of the background of the page is white.
And so what they're doing here, I'm going
to make this explicit, but
it should sound obvious
the moment I say it, is they're using
this background color change
from a very light gray
with brightness 93 to white,
with a brightness of 100.
And that background color
change means everything
with one background is part
of one logical grouping called the header
and everything with a
white background is part
of another logical
grouping called the content
of the page or whatever.
Now you may be thinking,
duh, that's obvious.
Well, that's, that's good.
It should kind of be obvious
or it should be obvious
in retrospect, I want to show you though
that they're also using
other elements to do that.
For instance, borders.
If you look at these little dropdowns
like the Seattle dropdown
all Seattle jobs, these
drop-downs have not only
they have a background color change
but they have an even stronger
dark gray border around them.
And likewise that border
is saying the same thing,
it's saying on one side of this border,
the inside is one
logical group, a dropdown
which includes say a label
and the little caret that tells
you, you should click here.
And then outside is, you
know, the rest of the page.
Technically they have a really fine border
on the bottom of their header as well.
And look, they have the same
background, color change
plus border strategy right
here around their logo
or what kind of stands in for their logo.
Let's see, do they have
anything going on over here?
Not really but like even the search bar
is the same sort of thing.
The search bar is a divider line.
So why am I bringing all this up?
One are the most important
lessons you can learn
about spacing is that
you can use white space
instead of any of these other separators.
Borders and lines are a type of separator.
Background color changes
are a type of separator.
So is spacing.
And that's not to say you
should always use spacing
but anytime you're trying
to make a design look neater
and cleaner and simpler,
you should at least think
can I use spacing instead of a line?
Or can I use white space
instead of a background color change?
And by the way, I use
the terms white space
and spacing interchangeably.
It doesn't have to be white.
This could be a dark UI with
white text, and I would still
call the empty pixels of dark
or black or whatever it is
spacing or white space.
It's just a matter of semantics.
All right, so let's try this idea.
Let's take this header
and delete the background.
And then if we're using spacing, you know,
perhaps we would be able to
just keep all of this stuff
at kind of where it is right
now, but I'm gonna move it down
just a bit, just to make it really clear
that it's separated from
this other content here.
And kind of get the sense of, okay,
especially if I put a little
more margin at the top here
so that the spacing is symmetric top
versus bottom spacing is
relatively similar here.
I can start to make it feel
like I'm communicating the separatedness
of the header from the
content, just using space.
And sure enough, that looks cleaner.
Now let's try doing the same
thing with these breadcrumbs.
Essentially what I'm
going to be doing is just
removing the borders.
But when the borders go,
I still would want this
to be something that
kind of looks clickable.
Like I'll be experimenting
a little bit here.
So I've got Seattle,
all Seattle jobs and media.
I guess it's really art media design.
And then, because these are breadcrumbs,
I'm going to need some
little separator character
in between them.
You can see, they just use a little caret.
I'm actually going to do a
character called a guillemets
which is used as quotes and
French and some other language
but in English it's generally unseen.
And so it can look kind of
cool to do something like that.
I'll go tidy up the
horizontal spacing here.
And eight pixel sounds good.
One thing I will do though
is probably pick maybe a slightly
darker default font color.
Then I can even remove
some of the attention
from these guillemets by
say, making them lighter,
60% opacity or something
could work out nicely.
Now, before I get ahead of myself,
I actually do want to
change the font here.
Right now, it's in the default Arial.
The entire site is so
that it loads quickly
but for the sake of
doing a visual touch up,
we'll pick something a little bit nicer.
I'm gonna go with freight
text, which is one
of the good font recommendations
from the topography unit.
I think it's super elegant,
and I think it works in a
wide variety of designs.
Now, in the alignment lesson, we talked
about aligning things such
that you get the greatest feel
of alignment with the
same number of elements.
For that reason, I'm going to align this
with the search bar rather
than just shoving it
up against the logo over there.
If 18 kind of becomes the default size,
I'm going to beef these up to 18 as well
and then I'll increase the
white space between them.
And then I can remove this divider line.
Again, all of this is just sort
of in the interest of
trying to remove elements
that are doing the same thing
that spacing could be doing.
And maybe I'll just make these
labels a little clearer too.
This could even be bold new posts.
It's kind of like a
primary action on the site.
For the Craigslist logo here,
it seems pretty clear that I
will just be writing Craigslist
in the same font I've already loaded.
At least that'll be a little bit quicker
to load than having some other image.
But one thing that might
be fun is I noticed, first
of all they Craigslist, their
actual logo is the peace sign
and in their kind of
text-based logo that you see
on their page since it's a
link that you have basically
by definition already been
to, it oftentimes shows
up as purple, which is the
color of the peace emoji.
So I think it'd be cool if we said, Hey
for this Craigslist
design, let's keep somewhat
in the spirit of keeping things very quick
to load and nimble and use the emoji
that everyone else already
has on their computer.
We could even grab a
purple from the emoji here
and then maybe I would use
that purple as a theme color.
So I'm actually just going
to make a square of it above
so I can really quickly
grab it whenever I need.
To me, this dark gray though
is looking maybe a little bit too light.
So maybe I will have a purple-ish gray.
Grab the hue I want.
And that seems like that should be fine.
But what I'm actually going
to do is take that gray
and I'll just make a rectangle
with that same color here.
This is just something
I would do before I end
up naming the colors in the Figma document
when I'm still kind playing around
with them I might want to just be able
to really quickly reference
them in one place.
And that's a very cheap
and easy way to do it.
Now, what I'm going to do is remove a few
of the elements that I
think are not very useful
on this particular page.
For instance, this art
media design should be kind
of clear that we're here
because it's going to say art media design
at the top of the page in the breadcrumbs
but also we'll have it say
that in the search as well.
So I'm going to remove it here.
This is a button to minimize the sidebar
which I don't think is super necessary.
So we can remove that for this
particular set of results,
there's only one page
which means just having a bunch
of greyed out buttons here
doesn't make much sense,
we could remove all those.
There's no other sort orders on this page,
besides newest, believe me, I checked.
So we're going to remove that.
Let's actually do a search
where the button or it
searches as you type
so that you don't need to
press a physical button.
We could remove that and save search.
We can think about putting
that somewhere else
in the sidebar where you
actually customize the search.
Oh, and then this, go figure.
On this particular page,
you can really only choose
between list and map.
Those are the only useful ones.
And even having map is very similar
to searching within a certain
radius of a certain location.
So let's just play with removing this.
If I was really working on this app,
I'm sure we'd have to figure
out some way to include it.
But seeing as this is a
teaching exercise about spacing,
now we have this awesome
example to talk about
all the spacing that is now
visible around this search bar.
Especially if we just make it a tad bigger
I'm gonna go ahead and add a shadow
and you don't need to worry
too much about these details.
I'm gonna give it a large blur
and then a slightly negative spread,
which will just make it
a little less visible.
Kind of a just a soft shadow.
I like this particular effect.
I'm going to try removing the stroke too,
see if that's enough.
Not really, probably
should keep it in there.
Now, I want you to observe
like just how much the space
around this search bar kind
of draws attention to it.
Especially if we kind of
move these filter boxes
out of the way, it just is
a lot more apparent here.
And if you consider
that basically everyone
who comes to this page is either going
to start skimming straight
through this list,
or they're going to have some
keyword location or whatever
that they just type directly
into here, like this bar
and this text are the most
important elements on the page.
And so having them just
be naturally visible
seems like a really good way to go.
So I'll put some text in there.
I always like to be as helpful
as possible in these little
hint texts in search bars.
We'll just make this a little bit bigger.
That's also going to draw
some attention to it,
and I'll make it a 50%
opacity, which is just nice
and light for kind of this
hint text that appears
before the user starts typing.
Now, as far as an icon,
I'm going to go grab, let's
do maybe the feather icon set.
Those icons are very soft
and they're just a bit larger
than material designer quantum.
So there we go.
I'm actually going to
make this the same color
as the text, should work nicely.
And then one thing I'm going
to do with this white space
is I'm going to be particular
about trying to make it symmetric.
You'll see that there's now 18 pixels
on three sides of this search bar.
And I could do 18 pixels here,
but I don't really need to per se, because
in some sense this text and this icon are
like considered one group and
they're within the search bar.
So the spacing within this group
between the icon and the
text should actually be less
than the space around the
icon or around this group.
This is just one example
of internal spacing being
less than external spacing.
So, you know, so I make
that a little bit smaller.
Certainly doesn't look any worse.
By the way just to be clear,
we're starting to see some other examples
of this internal spacing
versus external spacing.
Consider these breadcrumbs.
These are really just one group, right?
Like all four of these
elements interspersed
by these three elements, they fit together
very neat, neatly as a group, we refer
to them as the breadcrumbs
or like the navigation.
The spacing between each of
these elements is eight pixels.
And yet, if you look,
the spacing between say
that text element and the next
element down is 23 pixels.
Like these are one group and
the space within this group
the internal spacing is much
less than the external spacing.
And that just makes it clear to the user
what is logically related on the page.
I'll mention this a whole
bunch in this video.
It's super important,
and if you don't find yourself
doing it automatically
you should definitely be saying
to yourself internal spacing
is less than external spacing.
Now let's go back to the search bar.
Having all this white space
around the search bar is
great for making it visible
but just because white space
is kind of this preferred
almost exceptional means
of separating elements
does not mean it's the
only one that you can use.
You can definitely use other things.
And especially it's when
you use them in combination
with white space that
they become so powerful.
So we have this border here.
That's kind of, ho-hum.
One thing I'm thinking about
is like can I remove this border?
In fact, you saw me do it
earlier, just out of habit.
I didn't even know if it would work
and it turns out it kind of doesn't
there's not enough shadow
on the sides and the top
for it to be immediately
an obviously clear to users
that this search bar stands
apart from everything else.
But having a divider line or a border,
that's really only one
of the other ways of separating elements.
The other big one was a
background color change.
And here, what I could do is
actually color the entire rest
of the background of this
page, say to 96% brightness.
And now all of a sudden
it makes the search bar
pop even more.
Now that the corners are more apparent,
I'm going to give a slightly
more rounded radius to them.
That's six pixels just feels very friendly
and soft, kind of matches
the, feel this shadow.
Yeah, I'm liking this quite a bit.
One thing I might do though
just a bit is shorten the search bar.
I'm not sure
if there's actually a character
limit on these titles.
My guess is there probably is.
And since none of them
are actually very long,
there's not a ton of variability in them.
Let's just presume it's pretty short.
Let's try something like just
say 750 pixels of width here.
As we work on this text,
we might need to make
it a little bit larger
but just in general,
not having form controls
stretching on to infinity
is going to look better
in the long run.
Now, when we look at this
results list right here,
to me, it looks visually very cluttered.
And I know we just
changed the font, but even
when it was the previous font,
it's not like it looked good.
Like we start with an icon,
then we have gray text.
That's nice and aligned, which is good
but then there's hardly
any space, five pixels
between this gray text
and then the blue links
and all the blue links are jammed
in line with smaller
text of a different color
saying where the opportunity
actually is located.
And then some of them,
not that this is even
useful for a job posting,
but some of them have
the orange word pick here
because I guess the poster
attached some images as well.
And of course there are
then all followed by a trashcan icon.
So how do we use white
space to solve this problem?
Well, one of the things I would definitely
do is put a little more
space between the columns
but also I think I would just separate
out these locations into a third column.
Again, especially if
there's a character limit
on the title of the post
and we can guarantee that
we're not going to have a bunch
of running over to be
like two or three lines.
It just seems like an easy win
to get a little more alignment
out of the same information
and make the locations scannable.
So I've got some of this same stuff
that I can put on this page right here.
We'll take this, just scoot it
on down below so we can reference it.
But we'll start by aligning
the date, that looks good.
Then we'll put it in the post titles.
Maybe something like 32 pixels
of space is plenty there.
And then after that, we
will do the locations.
Now you might notice
I don't have this star
and I don't have this trash can yet.
My intention is
that you wouldn't actually see
the controls to star a post
or to remove it with the trashcan.
You wouldn't see those
icons until you're hovering
over the specific posts that
you want to take the action on.
This is a design decision
that can make the desktop
version feel even neater and cleaner.
Now it does present some issues.
For instance, on mobile,
we wouldn't be able to use
hover because there's no hover
on mobile and certainly to keep
things keyboard accessible,
we'd want to make sure that
those controls would appear
if someone was using, say
the tab key to use this app.
But let's just put on a
little hover state right here.
To figure out how tall the hover state is.
I always go and add up
the line height plus the
paragraph space, so that is 42.
I'm going to assume, let's see.
It feels about right, move it down.
Kind of centering on the text.
I'm going to remove the drop shadow here.
And then this white feels pretty bright.
So I'm actually going to give
it like maybe a 70% opacity.
It's going to be maybe a
bit of a subtle hover effect
but I still think it'll work out.
Just dragging my little hand
pointer, cursor guy here.
Boom, that doesn't look so bad.
Now, one problem you
might've noticed here.
And this is something we talked about
in the alignment lesson
is when you're trying
to align hover states, you will run
into weird issues where the hover state
you have to make a choice
between whether the content should line up
with the other stuff or the hover state,
which you see less should
line up with the other stuff.
In this case, I'm just
going to have the hover
state extend a little bit
beyond this line of alignment.
That doesn't strike me
as being too bad or too messy or anything.
So let's just do that.
I'll have it be symmetric on both sides.
And then of course I
can add in some rulers
into my document here
so that it's very easy
to align other things to them.
Now I just pressed option command P
to bring up the last extension I used,
the feather icons extension,
and I'm going to grab the star
and we also want the trashcan, perfect.
Now I'm just going to put some amount
of space in between them.
Really, all I want to do is make sure
that each has enough where they kind
of have their own hover
state square right here
but I'm not going to worry too much
about the exact sizing here.
Just looking at where we're at so far,
there's two quick changes
I'm going to make.
First of all because these icons
are a little heavy compared
to the text, I'm actually going
to make them slightly less opacity,
maybe 80% or thereabouts would be fine.
And then the other thing
I'm going to do is just put
like a little title that says
search results or something
and maybe has a count of the
number of search results.
So I'll do that, we'll
make the line height auto
cause right now it's
something ridiculously long.
And let's just say there's
whatever, maybe 21 results here.
One thing I can also do is
capitalize these search results.
That draws a little bit
more attention to the label.
But if I do that,
oftentimes what I also want
to do simultaneously is make
the label a bit smaller.
So in this case, maybe 15 instead
of 18 and I can also make
it a little bit lighter.
So something like 80% opacity
this is a common text design
pattern that we'll talk
about in the topography unit,
but I call it the slub pattern
for smaller, lighter
case, uppercase and bold.
And it's something that a lot
of really good designers
use way more frequently
than you might imagine.
Once we have it here, we can also say
put it over here and just
say something like filter.
And now we have this neat parallelism
between the filters and the
search results themselves.
Now I just want to call
your attention once again
to the idea that internal spacing is less
than external spacing.
So certainly we have this
list of different job
opportunities here and
the space between any one
of these is just a couple pixels.
Right, they're basically
however tall we said this was,
42 pixels tall, and
they're just all stacked
on top of each other, not a whole ton
of space in between them.
Then there's just a little bit of space
between the label and the
thing that the label refers to.
So here's the search results label.
Here's the search results.
And we have 10 pixels of
space in between them.
You can then consider this
kind of its own logical group
right, and internal to this,
this 10 pixel little margin
right here is actually less
than the space external to this group.
So if we look here, now we have 30 pixels
between the label and
the search bar above,
which of course is its own type of group.
And so in really good
designs, you're just going to
be able to go kind of up and
down the ladder of groupings
and always find that your
internal spacing is less
than your external spacing.
Like, you know, once we
get to the search bar,
we've already done it with the search bar
but all the spacing in the
search bar is less than 30,
which is the external spacing.
All right, now let's work
on these filters a bit.
The first thing I want
to do is I'm definitely
going to be making this
text a little bit bigger.
We'll go with the same default font size
that we have right here,
which I believe was 18.
Of course if this text is 18,
we probably don't want quite
so small a line height.
So let's try just doing auto,
which that's going to be 23 pixels
and no space between paragraphs
and see where that gets us.
Honestly, going through these filters,
i think some of them we
could probably remove
and some of them we might
even be able to combine.
So for instance has image
just doesn't strike me
as very useful in job listings.
Of course, all this sort of stuff,
if I was working for
Craigslist as a client
I might push to remove this filter
when I'm looking at job
listings in particular.
But if there's a real strong
reason why it is useful
then like by all means I'd keep it.
I just, as a designer,
I always want to default
to removing things that I think
are going to be less used,
less useful, and just
generally taking up space.
We'll talk about subtler
strategies for hiding elements
besides simply removing
them a little bit later
in this unit, search
titles only, posted today,
that's easy enough to
see bundle duplicates.
That feels like something
that should be on by default,
someone shouldn't get rewarded
for posting the same thing 20 times a day
include new nearby areas.
And then we also perhaps
can just start putting
in these other like job type filters here.
Now, when I do this in Figma sometimes,
what I'll do is I will press shift enter.
So that's going to do like
essentially same line break
as there would be from
if there was just a line
of text that overflowed to the next line
but then I'm gonna press enter here
and I'll start typing the
next filter internship.
And then I'll press shift, enter
for non-profit and I'll press
shift, enter for telecommute.
Or that actually is just remote.
It's how we say it these days.
All right, and then if I do put
in a paragraph spacing, what happens is
where I pressed enter, the
paragraph spacing gets applied
but where I pressed shift
enter, it's only line height.
There's no paragraph spacing
applied in between these lines.
This is cool because it
allows me to use one text box
to just have like kind of sub categories.
This is by the way,
another internal spacing
smaller than external spacing.
Search titles only and
include nearby areas
are two filters that kind of
apply a just one level, there
they're sort of non-specific
to job posts, but then this
next group internship, nonprofit
and remote are all specifically
job related filters.
So they're a little bit
closer to each other cause
they're more logically related.
And then there's a small space
in between them and the other filters.
And I'm on the fence as to
whether or not full-time
part-time contract and
employees choice really
need to be their own group.
But let's just say that they are, I guess.
Again, I'm using shift
enter for these right here.
I'm going to get rid of these,
this stuff.
This miles from zip
control is pretty useful.
So we'll come back to it in a sec.
Now what I'm going to do is
because this text is bigger,
I will make these boxes a
little bit bigger as well,
maybe something like 17 pixels.
Then I'm going to get them roughly aligned
with the baseline of the text
and increase the spacing.
Here we go.
These, I think I need to move
down an extra, was it 10?
Yeah. 10 pixels right there.
And then I can grab these
three, drag them down to here.
And one more rounds it out.
Yes, they all have equal
spacing, six pixels.
Now can you tell the next
change that I'm about to do?
When you look at this, does
something look a little bit off?
To me, what I want to do is add in
just a little more space here.
So like let's say this
is maybe eight pixels,
but be careful I don't
want to add so much space
that the distance between a checkbox
and the label for that checkbox,
because these things
are one group is greater
than the space between
this group and this group.
This is just another internal spacing
external spacing sort of thing.
I don't want these
smushed in here like this
but I do want to have kind
of logical separation of
this one line the next.
And if I don't believe that
I'm quite getting there,
I can like certainly go
and add a little bit
more line height here.
Let's see what is this?
26 pixels, bring it down to 25.
Now what I've done is added
even more space between these
which should give me a little more leeway
to have space between each
checkbox and its own label.
To me, that feels pretty
good just like that.
Honestly, if I was going
to change something
I think I would probably
decrease this space.
But the reason this space feels too big is
because it's actually
feels a little bit greater
than the space
between this label and the
thing the label applies to,
which is this whole group.
So the spacing internal to
this group, which is here
and here should be less than
the spacing with the label.
We'll get those nice and lined up.
All right, now, the last thing I have left
to do is add this little miles
from zip filter right here.
So I'll go make a label for it.
Miles from zip, I'll uppercase it.
And I want the space
between the miles from
zip label and this group
of filters to be greater
than even the space here
or the space here because this label
and its group of filters
is one logical grouping.
And the external spacing
between this group of filters
and this group of filters,
which is really just these
two needs to be greater
than any of the other
spacings that we have here.
So miles from zip, that's nice.
I have a text box.
So what I'm going to do
is steal the one text box
on this page and I'll
make it much smaller.
And I'm also going to reduce
the size of the shadow.
This is something again,
don't worry about it.
We'll talk about it more soon.
But the idea here is this
text box is really not
as raised up from the
surface of the screen.
It's not as important,
so we don't need as much
shadowing around it.
So one thing I'll do is go
look at what this margin is.
That's 13 pixels do, maybe not 13
but something pretty similar here.
See how that feels, decent.
And then, because these are hint texts,
I'll make them lighter,
50, 60% opacity is good.
And then update search,
I'm going to remove
because that should be done automatically.
Reset, I might also remove
because it's only unclicking a few boxes
or we could have a reset button appear
once the user has actually
done some searches
and the same thing for save search.
I don't necessarily need
to give someone the option
to save a search until after
they've actually entered one.
I might be being touch fast
and loose with really just
kind of getting everything
down to the simple bare bones elements
but it is actually a real strategy.
And I will use this
with my clients where just
every little element, I'll say
how much do we really need this?
It's something that we
will be talking about more
in this unit, because
it's super important.
Now I'm just going to give
this a little bit more spacing.
You can see it's kind
of running into the miles from zip here.
I don't really want that.
And I'm going to take this sidebar.
And I think I just kind
of inherited this 10
or 11 pixel spacing from the
original version of the app.
But when I have kind of this
whole page at my disposal,
I could put in a little more space there,
something like 24 pixels, of
course, spacing by default.
I don't want it to be symmetric.
So maybe I moved that into.
And all of a sudden I am looking
at a much better version of this same app
when we zoom out and look
at the before and after.
It's just a total world
of difference here.
All right, and now I want to
switch gears a little bit.
I want to talk about
another aspect of spacing
with maybe a little bit more
elemental of an example.
When we just have text on a page.
And to me this is a really
important test piece
of your design skills.
Can you take just a
headline, maybe a subheader,
and some text and style
it really, really well.
What I'm going to do with
this example is first
I'm just going to do the white space stuff
and then we're going to
like pick a different font
to use and whatever kind
of make the last details
but you'll be able to see just
how much better we can get
it using this silly default
times font where it just looks
like totally unstyled HTML,
just a totally plain webpage.
We're going to get as far as we can
styling with white space,
and then and only then
will we apply some nicer fonts
just so you can see how far
we can get with white space.
Like this last example is really cool
but many of the things
that make this look better
aren't specifically white space.
It's not like Craigslist
design, it's a little bit messy.
And we talked about the
principles of spacing
as we cleaned it up
but it's not like it just lacks for space.
So now let's look at this other example
and see what can we do just using spacing.
So my particular example here
is part of the first chapter
of Greg Egan's excellent
scifi novel "Diaspora."
For those of you following
along at home, the fact
that it's a scifi novel
is maybe a little bit
of a hint of what type of brand we'll try
and hit when it comes time
to pick out some fonts.
So here's our new duplicated frame
and let's get to work.
Now, like I said this is just what
an unstyled HTML page looks like.
And if you, like me, came to design by way
of development, you've
probably had some texts
on the page at some point in
a browser that looks like this
before you've gotten around
to writing all the CSS styles.
I want to take just a minute
and talk about kind of
what being a developer did
for my mindset with white space.
Because when I created my
first web projects, you know
if I had a whole bunch of texts like this,
I would think, okay
I'm going to add in some
margins here, but I want
to add, I want to pick a
reasonable amount of margin to add.
So what's reasonable, like
20 pixels or something?
20 sounds pretty reasonable,
30 pixels, right?
Maybe 30 pixels on top,
30 pixels on the side.
And you know, 30 pixels in from this side
or something like, you
know, if someone were
to say, well you should just
add in 500 pixels of space.
It's like, wow, that,
hey, pretty good, 505.
That number would seem so
big and, and meaningless.
And I wouldn't even necessarily consider
adding in this much margin on one side.
Just doesn't make any sense.
Even if I know the screen
is going to be quite large.
So I had this mindset
of white space is
something that one adds in.
You start with all this content
and then you specifically write lines
of code that add a
little white space there.
Boop, add a little white space there
maybe some white space
here whatever it is.
That mindset is not useful for design.
For design, I think it's
much better to almost feel
like you're starting from
a blank piece of paper,
and then you're adding in
elements one at a time.
So if I was adding in just this title,
I might say, Hmm, you know what?
I'm totally going to center it here.
Or maybe I don't want to center it.
Maybe I want it to left align it.
But you know, the content I'll just have
in one little column right here
or maybe it will be kind
of tastefully offset
or something like that.
But when I see the frame as a blank page,
I start to think about every
element that I add being taking
away white space strategically rather
than white space being
something that's added one line
of code at a time in quote
unquote, reasonable amounts.
So let's fast forward here.
How would I approach this today?
Well, the Learn UI design
way of doing things is
to say, listen every bit
of white space that we add,
along with all these
other elements, they need
to solve problems because
design is not art,
design is solving a problem,
very often a business problem.
When we go to do something
like let's say add,
what would be the first
margin you would add?
Probably some space on the sides here.
When you add space
to the left and to the right of this text
what's the problem that
you're trying to solve?
It should be fairly obvious.
The problem is these line
links will just go to infinity.
They're completely unbounded.
If you had a monitor that
was 10,000 pixels wide,
you would have texts
that would go all 10,000
of those pixels.
And even if I couldn't even
read it, cause it was so far off
to the right, that text was
still just keep on going.
The problem we're trying
to solve by adding left
and right margin is the
infinite line length problem.
We want lines that are short enough
that like not only do we
not have to turn our head
to go from the beginning,
from the end of one line
to the beginning of
the next, but it's easy
to keep track of where
in the document you are
as you go from one line to the next.
Now spoiler alert, we've already talked
about what the ideal line length was
and the introductory unit I even said
it's 50 to 75 characters,
which is generally,
I always do that as
two to three alphabets.
So I've just entered my little ATEX code
to enter the alphabet three times.
And I'm actually
I'm going to make this,
Oh, this is Georgia.
This should actually be
times, huh, there we go.
There's that default text that we want.
Go ahead and make sure this is the same.
Anyhow with this text box,
now we can see that this three alphabet,
roughly 75 character string
right here being kind
of a natural max width for
the text box is telling us
we either need to make
this text box smaller
or we need to make the font bigger.
And we could do a little bit
of each like we could
say, this will be 19.
I'm not going to be too strict
about whatever this size is here.
I reserve the right to change the width
of this text box as this font changes,
and as the font size changes.
So if at the end of this,
we change fonts and then we
want to change sizes again,
that might also necessitate
us changing the width
of this text box.
That being said, if we had
oh whatever let's just do 18 here.
Yeah, maybe something
like this, let's do 530
and I'm gonna do the same thing here.
They're all going to be
given a width the 530
and they all should be
aligned with one another,
but there we go.
I can take this, group it,
and press option H to
center it in my page.
Now I'm just going to ungroup
it, command shift G, cool.
We've added in the biggest white space
on the page, the white space
that's on the right
side and the left side.
And by doing so, we've solved
the infinite line length problem.
We've now made this reading
text an ideal line length,
somewhere in the vicinity of
50 to 75 characters per line.
Now this strikes me as good
for a couple of different reasons.
First of all, it's easier
to read, that's awesome.
Second of all these margins
add a lot of breathing room.
And third of all,
even beyond just having
breathing room here,
I just have this sense of like,
this was, this is non
default, we have went
from a totally default
webpage that makes you
think you're seeing some
technical website that's been
up since 1995 to seeing
something that a little
more care was put into, not
much, but just a tiny bit.
All right, now let's look at the next type
of spacing that you'd probably add
which is the spacing above this header.
Again, we're going to use
white space to solve a problem.
So let's say, what problem are we solving
by putting white space above this header?
One of our laws of white
space was to use white space
to make things look presented
or to draw out focal points.
So to some degree, this
chapter one, then the title
of chapter one, that is a
focal point of the page.
And so white space will kind
of surround it probably more
than any other element so
that it appears like a focal point should.
But we can also use our
strategy from the first unit
of saying let's fail left and fail right.
And say like, what is too small
a value of white space for
the top, like 10 pixels?
Yeah, that doesn't even look
like any white space, frankly.
That could be the browser
default and no one wrote any CSS
to make things look more designed.
What would appear like too much?
Well, here's one answer.
Tell you if this tech started halfway
down the page on a desktop
monitor, I would think is there
like supposed to be an image
here that's not loading
or something, like this
just feels awkward.
So we're definitely not going to do that.
Let's pick a solution,
we're going to go probably
a little bit closer
to the lower bounds here
of having no white space.
But what does this turn out to be?
88 pixels of white space.
Cool, at least for our intents
and purposes right now,
88 works just fine.
Now, when we look at this
little element right here,
this is styled as a level
two header an H two and HTML
but it's not really so
much a header as it is kind
of the time and place where
this chapter takes place.
It's the setting.
So I'm actually going to use
the default text styling here
and I'll just do option
command C to copy the style,
option command V to paste the style.
And then I'm going to unbold it
by of course, pressing control B.
There's a little bit of
extra line spacing there
which I'm going to remove for right now,
cause that's kind of awkward.
And there we go.
That actually looks better
even just like that.
But then one other thing I'm going
to do is this chapter
one, in some sense is kind
of like a label for the
name of the chapter.
So I'm actually just going to put the name
of the chapter here
but I'm going to put a label
above it that says chapter one.
I think it needs a
colon, let's add a colon.
Yeah, there we go. That's
a little bit better.
All right, now I'm just going to kind of
put in some white space
here so it feels neat.
And just going to kind of like mess around
with things just a little bit,
actually, honestly this
feels pretty good how it is.
Yeah, there we go, I like this.
Now look in some sense,
this is actually, if I,
if I did this, correct, let's see here,
this should be an example
of external spacing being
greater than internal spacing.
So what, what's the most
internal spacing we have?
What's the logically, the
smallest little group,
is probably this chapter one label,
and then the name of chapter one.
And what's the spacing
between these things?
There's none, there's zero pixels
of space between these two text boxes.
And by the way, when you're
checking internal spacing
and external spacing with text here again
the space of the text
like on one hand, that zero
pixels of space, right?
That's zero pixels of visual space.
And the visual is ultimately what matters
but generally it can be a good shorthand
to check just how far apart
the bounding boxes are
but don't necessarily think
that for text it's kind
of the be-all-end-all.
Visually what you want to do is make sure
that the internal spacing
always appears less
even if the numbers are
a little wonky in places.
All right, so then I have chapter one
and the name of chapter one.
Let's consider this little
setting element here.
Now, this setting for chapter one,
does that seem more related
to the title of chapter one
or does that seem more related
to content of chapter one?
To me it almost feels
like it's more a sub property
of the title itself, right?
It's kind of like the
metadata about this chapter.
It's not really content.
And so it more seems like it fits
in a group with these elements
rather than in a group
with the text itself.
And consequently, if
you look here, let's see
this is 22 pixels of space.
Yeah, and this is 38 pixels of space.
So if you then consider
this as the smallest group,
the internal spacing is zero.
If you consider this as
the next smallest group,
the internal spacing is 22.
If you then consider this
as another group down here
it's the external spacing, 38 pixels.
So just kind of eyeballing
things, I have gotten
to the point where I'm naturally going
to start thinking what kind
of belongs near one thing or the other.
It's not to say, you always need
to do this but if you don't
find yourself doing it
the vast majority of the time,
just be repeating yourself
as you design, internal spacing
less than external spacing.
Your goal is to follow the rule explicitly
until it just becomes this
automatic unconscious process.
All right, so maybe I would
also just add in something that
was like the name of the novel "Diaspora"
and it's by Greg Egan.
So maybe what I would do is put
in a little dash between
the names, actually, sorry
a dash as this character, let's add this.
I'm going to put in a longer form of dash.
There is the n-dash
which you can create by
pressing option and then dash
or there is if you press
shift option dash, the m-dash.
And this is the longest
one, not every font has it
but it's kind of cool looking.
And it's like, since
most people don't use it,
it's so long that it looks
like a little more designed.
Of course, I'll just give
this just a bit of space
and there we go.
And this is really its own group, right?
This is kind of the nav.
It's not really related
to this content at all.
Let's see, in fact
is this 45 pixels of space,
even greater than this.
So even adding this in like
all the internal spacing
and external spacing constraints here,
I am following unconsciously, pretty cool.
Okay, it's at this point
though, that I want
to direct your attention to
both of them at the same time
just bask in how much better this looks.
Like, this is still the same
unstyled obnoxious times font that you see
on a website where there's
no styling entered,
but even so this is a
world apart from this.
In fact, if someone showed
me this and it was like
I'm not a designer, I
think, yeah, you are.
We may not have picked any
fancy fonts for this, but just
from the white space alone,
it feels much more considered.
Okay, so now we're at the
point where I do actually
want to pick a couple of fonts.
And then once I do that,
we'll be able to talk about
the space between paragraphs,
the space between lines, the
space, even between characters.
The thing is how you talk
about that changes depending on the font.
So I want to make sure
we have the fonts nailed,
and once those are dialed
in, then we will switch
over to talking about the
details of spacing within text.
I'm not going to go into super
depth on how to pick fonts
in this unit, but I will just say, okay
knowing that this is a
scifi book, I'm going to
be picking some kind of more
squared off or geometric fonts.
When I saw all these numbers here,
I immediately thought I
should use a monospace font.
Well, one of my favorite monospace fonts
is one called carbon, which
is very scifi feeling.
This is nice because all the numbers
then line up from line to line.
And I can just copy
that and paste it here,
that same style and paste it here.
That's good right there.
All of a sudden, my m-dash becomes like
an underscore character.
So I'm going to need to do something else
to distinguish the title of
the book from the author.
That should be fine.
And carbon, like many
fonts is one that is good
but it's even better upper case.
When I make that uppercase,
it just looks even crisper
and cleaner and better.
But one thing I am going
to do is shrink it too.
Again this is just one more thing
that's just going to have it
appear a little bit crisper.
It's a weird effect, but
that happens to text plenty.
You make it just a little bit smaller
and yeah, it might get harder to read
but it just feels a little bit crisper.
That's really the best
word I can think of for it.
The spacing is starting to get messed up
as I pick out fonts here, so we'll just
get through it and then readjust things.
For the title, another one of the fonts
that I most recommend is abolition
which is just incredibly geometric
and angular and looks very
good in a scifi setting,
I mean, along with the
zillion other settings,
I really love it.
Now, if I have this here
picking the exact font size
is not something I can
really commit to right now.
What I'd want to do is see
how long are all the chapter
titles in this whole book?
Because if there's some
that are going to be three lines long,
then this will probably
be a little bit smaller.
However, if they're all only one word,
then I can probably more safely
make this default font size
a little bit bigger.
Font sizes, and the actual
real data that they apply to
is like one of those
chicken and egg problems
in design where you should
never fully finally commit
to one before you've seen the other.
Even then they'll continue
to inform each other.
And the work of design just never ends.
For the body font, I
actually tried a couple
of different ones but the one I landed on
was this Google font called Noticia Text.
And Noticia is awesome
because it's a serif font,
It feels a little bit more stately.
It's good for long form
reading, it's very readable.
But if you look at these letter forms,
they're like not angular,
but they're like a
little more squared off.
This isn't just like a round O,
and it's not like it's a full-on rectangle
in the middle here, but just that hint
of rectangularness makes
this play very nicely
with these fonts where, I mean
literally they're geometrical shapes.
You know, it's a good balance
between something you
need to read for hours
at a time and something
that fits in a scifi book.
I might do something with
some of these labels here,
but if I make them bold, I
might kind of counteract them
by making them just a little
bit lighter too, 80%, 90%.
There we go, okay, and this text, it looks
like this is kind of
on the short side now.
I might try, Oh, whatever,
let's just go with 17.
All right, that strikes me as good enough
for picking fonts at least for
a little exercise like this.
Let's talk about now, some
of the spacing inherent
to this body text here.
First there's the space between lines.
Now, again, if we're going to
do this Learn UI design way
we're going to say what
problem is the space
between lines trying to solve?
Well, there's a really
obvious answer to that.
There's space between lines
so that your eyes can track
from the end of one line to
the beginning of the next line.
And so we want there to be enough space
so that that's easy to do.
One of the easiest ways
to test for that is just
to like read a paragraph.
Okay, so as I read a little
bit, I'm just making sure
that my eyes can easily
track from one to the next.
And that seems to be the case.
Now this is interesting
because let's say 23,
we'll make it explicit.
That's what that value is.
Could even bump it up one
probably not going to be any harm in that.
I just want to tell you,
you'll probably see out there
some people recommending doing
things like giving you ratio.
So 24 divided by 17.
24 divided by 17, 1.4.
So some people say, Oh,
1.4, 140% is, you know
good letter spacing.
Actually that is a number that
I've seen 140% is the best
excuse me, not letter spacing,
the best line height to use,
but the truth is the line height,
it just totally depends on the line.
It depends first of all, on the font
because different fonts have
different line heights built
in sort of naturally, but it also depends
on the length of the line,
because the purpose of line
height is to make it easy
to go from one line to the next.
If there's not very many
characters per line,
such as in a title, the
very long title that goes
on forever, then I don't
need 140% line height here.
Like that is ridiculous.
In fact, even if I just did,
let's say auto that's 68.
Okay, so we've got a 68
and then we'll just start making it lower.
You know, as long as the
characters aren't touching
like here or they're
touching, I, that's not
the look I'm going for,
that would be an effect,
but as long as they're not touching,
there's enough space, you know
the space is not the problem here.
There's so few characters
per line that I have no problem going
from long to title, that's simple.
But in body text, that's a
much tougher thing to do.
So that's when we start
adding in a lot more space.
So 140, that's one way to think about it.
What was this before?
Did we say 26 or 27 or something?
Maybe it was a little bit less.
In general, failing left
is when the letter forms
are hitting each other, and failing right
is when there is so much space
in between the lines that you
could put whole other lines
in between your lines.
Yo dawg, you don't want to do that.
Like, that's one thing if
you're printing out a paper
for someone to write a
bunch of comments on,
but it's not really a good
thing to do for web design.
Yeah, that seems good enough.
So I just pick this
font and this font size
and then that kind of
affects the line length.
But also if I make the line
length longer than, you know,
at some point, if I go
all the way out to here,
I'm going to want to
have more line spacing
so that it's easier to go
from the end of one line to the next.
So it all kind of feeds back into itself.
You want to get the characters per line,
the font size, and the line
height all lined up perfectly.
All right, so now that we have that,
let's actually remove these alphabets
since we don't need them.
And now we'll talk about the
space in between paragraphs.
So first question, what's the goal
of putting a space in between a paragraph?
Well it's to let you know
that there's a little bit
more emphatic of a break
between here and here
than there is between say here and here.
Honestly, it's just another version
of external spacing is
greater than internal spacing.
The space within a paragraph,
that is the line height,
is going to be less than the
space between paragraphs.
So a failing left in
this case is having no
paragraph spacing whatsoever.
There, I mean like, look, when I do this,
I can't even tell where
this paragraph begins.
Right, because there's
no, there's no clue.
Failing right, on the other hand
would be adding so much paragraph spacing
that it just looks like
a double line break.
It looks like I was here
and I pressed enter enter,
and there's no actual paragraph spacing.
It's just kind of a double enter.
Again, that's fine if you have to like
put some, type something
out on a typewriter,
but in digital design we
can pick a value that's
in between zero and the full line height.
So that a paragraph space looks
like a different type of space.
It looks designed.
It's just like, it's a little clue.
It's not, it's not the
biggest thing in the world
but it's just going to add to that sense.
Now I will be honest,
you're going to hear
other designers recommend
that you do something
different, many designers
praise baseline grids,
where they have a grid
of say eight pixels or 10
pixels or whatever it is.
And then they line up
texts so that the baseline
of the text is on one of these grid lines
for every single line, for
the header, for everything.
And sometimes the grids will be small
such that there's two or three
rows here per line of text.
And sometimes there'll be bigger
where perhaps they're just on one line.
If you do that system,
you may end up having kind
of that double line break
style paragraph space.
I'm not going to discourage
you from doing a baseline grid.
I will say though that
I think it is better
to have a paragraph space that is
in between zero and the full
value of the line height,
just so it does appear
like its own type of space.
But I'll also say if you don't
do a baseline grid already,
it's really not worth necessarily getting
in the habit of it, and the reason why is
because it won't make a
bad design look better.
A bad design still looks
bad when you apply a great
baseline grid and a good design
just can still look great
even if it's totally off the grid.
All right, rant over.
Let's talk a little bit
about the third and
final type of space here.
We talked about space
between lines and texts.
We talked about space between paragraphs.
Let's talk about space between characters.
For the most part again, ask yourself
what problem are we trying to solve
by adding letter spacing
or subtracting it?
Well, if the font is
well-designed and you're using it
as intended, there is no problem
to solve for the most part.
Honestly, it's a very
common beginner mistake
to add letter spacing,
to sentence case text.
Just text that should be sent normally.
And I think
as you grow and sort of your
gut instinct of design, when
you see this sort of thing, it
will become obnoxious to you.
It appears too loose and too spaced out.
And sure enough, like that's
not how the font was designed.
Now, one of the exceptions
to this is when you're using uppercase.
When you're using uppercase,
in some sense, you're not using
the font as it was designed.
You're kind of doing the special edge case
of what you can do with a font.
And so then it's actually
much more acceptable
to add in some letter spacing.
And you can see that,
that that actually looks kind of cool.
Like I didn't even realize how
cool that was going to look.
I don't know if I would keep it like that.
And that's pretty dramatic,
14% letter spacing here.
Like that's quite a bit,
but the point is it works a
lot better with uppercase.
For the most part, you're
never going to be putting
in letter spacing into
sentence text like this.
You're really only going to be adding it
if you're working with uppercase here.
And just to be fair, abolition, this font
this is an uppercase only font.
So it was actually designed
with upper case in mind.
I would not add in letter spacing here
since I guess it does kind of look cool
but just by default, it's not like I need
to simply because it's already uppercase.
The biggest exception you'll see
to this is occasionally some titles
especially when you use say like kind
of grotesque fonts as a category of fonts
we'll be talking about more
in the topography unit.
Well then I might actually
for, if something was
like a headline remove a
little bit of letter spacing
and neat and clean
but that's really kind
of the only main place
where I'm going to be
removing letter spacing
and uppercase is the only
place where I'm going
to be adding it in.
If you're using a font as
designed like right here,
then I'm just going to leave this be.
Oh, and by the way, like,
even though this is uppercase
because it's a monospace
font, I feel like, Hmm
I don't necessarily need to add in any.
And I don't know that I would get anything
by adding in letter spacing right there.
So we'll leave that be too.
All right, before and after, how'd we do?
It's not too bad, right?
Let's just talk about a couple
other things that come up
whenever we start talking
about white space.
The first is landing pages.
Landing pages are one end of the spectrum
where you're just going to
add white space like crazy.
So let's look at this headline,
lab management made easy.
If I look here and I do a
little pixel measurement
I've got something like 180
pixels of space right here.
And that was probably
hard-coded, a developer wrote
yeah, we just want 180 pixels
of space above this headline.
When I was a developer at least,
I would have thought that
seems very excessive.
But again the goal is not
to make these numbers seem reasonable,
it's to make the visual
end result very pleasing.
And how they're doing that
is they're putting this nice
crisp, clear image behind it.
And they have the headline
and this is roughly vertically
centered within this space.
That's great, works fine.
Another example.
And we don't even need to scroll to see it
is look at this header.
This is actually quite big for a header.
I rarely would design a header
that is all of 110
pixels tall or something.
But it is interesting to see
that of this font right here,
this little text that says tour
and has the nav destinations.
It's like roughly 10 pixels
tall, the space below it,
that is roughly 54 pixels tall.
So this is like 90% white space.
Again, as a developer, this
would have blown my mind.
It was something that when I noticed
that this is what
professional designers did,
I was like, wow, I am not
using spacing the correct way.
So when I say double your white space,
I just mean there's going
to be a lot of times
where you're adding much more
than you otherwise would have thought.
And probably the best
heuristic to help you there is,
like I said time and time
again, fail left, fail right.
Figure out what looks like
definitely too little.
Figure out what it looks
like definitely too much.
And then go somewhere in between.
Knowing that, I almost feel
like that's too little.
I feel like they could add
a little space right here.
I'm not even sure if it's supposed
to be related to this stuff.
Maybe because these are case studies,
and these are people who use
them, but still it does feel
like there should be a
little bit more space there.
And that's not a huge deal.
I don't mean to throw too much shade here.
Quartzy is actually designed
by Wayno which is a fantastic design firm.
They do very, very good work.
I just wanted to point this out
because on one hand, landing pages are one
of the places where people are just,
you're going to add in
a ton of white space,
maybe even more so than you
would in comparable pages
throughout the rest of your app.
To make that clear, here's
an example from Quartzy's
actual order requests
form page inside the app.
And you'll see that
there's a lot more data
on this page, right?
This is actually a
pretty data heavy table.
There's a lot going on here,
there's a bunch of information
about all these different
things you can order
for your lab, et cetera.
And, and honestly, it's pages like this
where people give me the most pushback.
They say double your white space.
What if I have a lot
of information to show?
And my reply is you can
still often have a lot
more white space than
you'd otherwise expect.
If you look, this page feels
very generously laid out.
Like there's a lot of white space.
There's plenty of white space here.
Let's start measuring stuff again.
50 pixels above this button or 54 pixels.
Even say as padding around
these groups right here,
25 pixels high, 35 pixels
on the sides, et cetera.
You get the point here.
I mean, you could do the
same exact measurements.
We can figure out
what percentage of this
button is actually taken up
by the text and what is
just padding, et cetera.
I just want to show this example
because it makes it clear
that just because you have this page
with a lot of data, you need to show,
it does not mean that you
can't have white space
that everything needs to
be super smushed together.
Now I will say that the more
data you do need to show,
like for instance, these
designers judged acceptable
than a normal desktop screen,
I would only see two actual
items and a title, right?
Like that may be too little.
Someone might say, no, you know what?
We need greater information density here.
I want to be able to
see four of these things
the moment I load up the page.
Yeah, if that's the case,
we would do some things
to rework the white space,
rework how probably how these
columns are done, et cetera
but just because you need
to display a lot of data
does not mean you shouldn't
be including white space
or trying to include as
much spacing as possible.
And when you do run into
a situation like that,
the only other pointer I will say is
pay attention in particular,
then to all the other lessons
that we covered in the fundamentals unit.
Alignment becomes all the more important
if you have to have a little less space
than you otherwise would like to.
Consistency becomes a
little more important when
you're not going to get away
with showing just a few things,
you still have to show a ton of things.
And the last thing I'll mention
is just about mobile apps.
Seriously, all the examples we've looked
at so far have been desktop apps.
And to me, that actually seems
fine because desktop apps
and mobile apps have the same
principles in these regards.
But if anything, working on a desktop app
affords you more natural room
to put in white space
and on the mobile app,
you're just not even going
to have the choice sometimes.
Like things are just going
to be kind of constrained.
That being said, when you
can really do a good job
of just showing the essential,
having it well aligned,
neat, clean, consistent
and plenty of generous spacing around it,
It's going to appear really, really good.
So fundamentally none of
the principles have changed.
It's just a little bit harder
to add in a ton of white space
when the screen is small.
One thing I will say,
I'll just throw this in
right at the very end.
It's just because it's a
pretty common beginner mistake.
On mobile, you really do want to make sure
that when you have a lot of
content to display on one page,
to the best of your ability,
you're using the entire page.
So for instance, at the time of recording
both Android and iOS typically
have 16 pixel side margins
on either side and most of
the content on your screen,
If you have to display a lot, you're going
to want to go all the way
from one side to the other.
If not from the very
borders of the screen,
then to that side margin line
on the left and on the right.
If you're doing that,
you're going to get this very consistent
horizontal spacing, but it
won't necessarily be a ton.
You'll do a lot more following of the law
of internal spacing, being
less than external spacing
and a little bit less doubling
your white space simply
because there's not the room to.
And there we have it
folks, that's spacing.
So I won't belabor this conclusion
by introducing any new ideas.
Just remember those four laws
of spacing and take a look
at the homework below.
It's about all there is to it.
Hope you enjoyed and we'll
see you in the next lesson.